<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="dcm4che2-installation" revision="1">
  <title>Installation Instructions</title>

  <sect1 id="dcm4che2-install" revision="1">
    <title>Minimum System Requirements and Supporting Software</title>

    <para>In order to start using dcm4che, you must first download the
    distribution from SourceForge. 
    To begin:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Download the binary distribution of dcm4che2 from the Files
        page of the dcm4che project page on SourceForge (<literal><ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/dcm4che/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/dcm4che/</ulink></literal>).
        The current version available for download is
        <literal>dcm4che-2.0.6.tar.bz2</literal>. If you plan on writing your own
        DICOM applications, it is recommended that you download the source
        distribution as well. The source may then be linked in with your IDE
        for debugging and browsing purposes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Extract the archive file to the directory of your choice.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
    <para>After extracting the contents, you should see the following directory structure:</para>
    
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
dcm4che-2.0.6
|
|_bin
|
|_dtd
|
|_etc
    |
    |_dcmof
    |
    |_logger
|
|_lib
|
|_xml
    ]]></programlisting>
    
        <para>This directory listing may be described as follows:</para>

        <variablelist spacing="compact">
            <varlistentry>
                <term>dcm4che-2.0.6</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This is the root directory, named by "dcm4che" and the version.  It doesn't 
                        contain anything other than the following subdirectories.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>bin</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>bin</literal> directory contains Unix and Windows scripts to run the sample applications.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>dtd</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>dtd</literal> directory contains DTD files which define the XML format of the DICOM data
                        dictionary used by dcm4che2, and the XML format of DICOM objects
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>etc</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>etc</literal> directory contains configuration used by the sample applications.  There are a
                        couple of subdirectories as well:
                        <itemizedlist>
                            <listitem>dcmof - information used by the Order Filler samples, currently only a sample Modality Worklist
                                            (MWL) Item (in XML format for submission to dcm4chee) resides here</listitem>
                            <listitem>logger - a sample log4j.properties file which defines a syslog appender.</listitem>
                        </itemizedlist>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>lib</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>lib</literal> directory contains the dcm4che2 libraries, all of the third party libraries that the toolkit 
                        depends upon, and individual JAR files for all of the samples.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>xml</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The <literal>xml</literal> directory contains the XML definition of the DICOM data dictionary, and the DICOM UIDs
                        that the toolkit will use.  These items are inclusive of the DICOM 2006 standard, and are actually generated from 
                        the standard documents during the build process.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

    </sect1>
</chapter>