<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="dcm4chee-services" revision="1">
  <title>dcm4chee Services</title>

    <sect1 id="services-overview">
        <title>Overview</title>

        <para>
            dcm4chee contains a number of services...
            XMBean and EJB infrastructure...
            diagram...
        </para>
    
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="services-ref">
        <title>Service Reference</title>
        
        <sect2 id="core-archive">
            <title>Core Archive Services</title>
            <para>
                The core archive services are implemented as EJBs and JBoss XMBeans.  They provide services to the 
                user interface, DICOM server, HL7 server, etc.  They are implemented within the <literal>dcm4chee-sar</literal>
                and <literal>dcm4chee-ejb</literal> code modules, and are configured by manipulating their XML descriptor files.
            </para>
            
            <sect3 id="ae-service">
                <title>AE Title Configuration Service</title>
                <para>
                     Used to list/add/remove AE configuration entities - alternatively to more convenient
   AE Management Page of the <ulink url='hliteralp://localhost:8080/dcm4chee-web/'>
   Administration Web Application</ulink>.
   Used/Required by various DICOM services (Query/Retrieve SCP, Storage Commitment SCU/SCP,
   DICOM Hanging Protocol SCP) to 'guess' the port number of DICOM peer Application Entities,
   if no AE configuration entry for a given AE Title matches.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="audit-service">
                <title>Audit Logger</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="comp-service">
                <title>Compression Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="cons-service">
                <title>Consistency Check Service</title>
                <para>
                    Sets up a schedule to automatically check the consistency of compressed images. 
                    You can set image compression rules in the Compression Service. You can also 
                    use it directly via JMX to manually check the consistency of images.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="cont-service">
                <title>Content Edit service</title>
                <para>
                    Identifies where patient information and study information updates are sent and received.
                 </para>
                 <para>
       		    Use the values in <literal>ReceivingApplication</literal> and <literal>ReceivingFacility</literal> aliteralributes or the 
                    <literal>SendingApplication</literal> or <literal>SendingFacility</literal> aliteralributes to configure specific
                    forwarding rules in the <literal>HL7SendService</literal> for patient information updates received from this
                    Content Edit Service. 
                </para>
                 <para>
                    Use the values in the <literal>CalledAETitle</literal> and the <literal>CallingAETitle</literal> aliteralributes to configure
                    specific forwarding rules in the <literal>StudyMgtScu</literal> Service for study information updates
                    received from this Content Edit Service.
                </para>
                 <para>
                     The Content Edit Service sends also <literal>PatientUpdated</literal> and <literal>SeriesUpdated</literal> JMX Notifications. 
                     This allows to forward instances to systems not supporting either StudyMgtScu or HL7 ADT patient updates.
                 </para>
                 <para>
                     In this case the receiver must use the received instances for updating!
                     Use the <literal>ForwardService</literal> to configure this forward option.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="dcm-service">
                <title>DICOM Server</title>
                <para>
                    Sends incoming service reqest to registered DICOM services. When 
                    configuring, select the TCP port listening port, the security protocol 
                    for communication, timeouts, and the maximum number of connected DICOM clients.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="dvc-service">
                <title>Device Service</title>
                <para>
                    Use the commands in this service to import device mapping files, delete 
                    device mappings, delete a specific device, get a list of all devices for a 
                    specific protocol, and add the scheduled station name AE title, the name, 
                    and the modality to the given SPS items.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="echo-service">
                <title>Echo Service</title>
                <para>
                    Use this service to test the AE configurations (host and port and protocol) you 
                    defined with the AE Configuration Service. First, you must set the CallingAETitle 
                    used in echo associations used to  test those AE configurations.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="export-service">
                <title>Teaching File and Clinical Trial Export Manager</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="fc-service">
                <title>File Copy Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="fix-pat-service">
                <title>FixPatientAttributes Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="forward-service">
                <title>DICOM Forward Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="fsm-service">
                <title>File System Management Service</title>
                <para>
                    Specifies the location of
                    file systems in which DICOM objects received from the Store SCP Server 
                    are stored. You can also set up rules to delete the most infrequently
                    accessed studies.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="gpwl-feed-service">
                <title>DICOM GPWL Feed Service</title>
                <para>
                    Used to add entries to the General Purpose Worklist, triggered by received MPPS N-Set messages.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="gpwl-scp-service">
                <title>DICOM GPWL Service Class Providers</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="gpwl-scu-service">
                <title>DICOM GPWL SCU Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="hang-service">
                <title>DICOM Hanging Protocol SCP</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="ian-service">
                <title>DICOM IAN/SCN SCU Service</title>
                <para>
                    Used to notify DICOM peers about available instances via Instance Available Notifications and Study Content Notifications.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="key-service">
                <title>DICOM Key Object Generation Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mcm-service">
                <title>DICOM Media Creation Management SCU</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="md5-service">
                <title>MD5 Check Service</title>
                <para>
                    Used to check if the MD5 sum of the new object differs
                    from the MD5 sum of the existing file. If the MD5 sum does not match, the files may be corrupted.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="move-service">
                <title>Move SCU Service</title>
                <para>
                    rocess move orders. Invokes DICOM 
                    Retrieve requests, typically from the archive's own DICOM
                    Query/Retrieve Service (SCP).
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mpps-em-service">
                <title>MPPS Emulator</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mpps-scp-service">
                <title>DICOM Modality Performed Procedure Step (MPPS) SCP</title>
                <para>
                    Used to define the calling and called AE titles for receiving MPPS messages.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mpps-scu-service">
                <title>DICOM Modality Performed Procedure Step (MPPS) SCU</title>
                <para>
                    Used  to forward MPPS messages received by
                    the MPPS SCP Service.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mwl-scp-service">
                <title>DICOM Modality Worklist SCP</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mwl-scu-service">
                <title>Modality Worklist SCU</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="pps-exc-service">
                <title>Performed Procedure Step (PPS) Exception Managment</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="pps-scu-service">
                <title>PPS SCU Service</title>
                <para>
                    Forwards GP-PPS messages received by the PPS SCP Service.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="qr-service">
                <title>DICOM Query/Retrieve SCP</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="mail-service">
                <title>Simple SMTP Mail Sender</title>
                <para>
                    Used to send email messages through SMTP.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="stgcmt-service">
                <title>DICOM Storage Commitment SCU/SCP</title>
                <para>
                    Provides a DICOM Storage 
                   Commitment Service in the Service Class Provider
                   (SCP) and the Service Class User (SCU) Role. When acting as the SCP,
                   the service handles storage commitment requests that it receives 
                   from modalities or evidence creators (workstations). 
                   When acting as the SCU, it may request storage
                   commitment for objects for itself that were retrieved from the archive to a remote
                   application. Typically this application is a further archive 
                   instance acting as a long-term or central archive.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="store-service">
                <title>DICOM Storage SCP</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="st-info-service">
                <title>Study Information Service</title>
                <para>
                    Used to retrieve information about a study, or about a series of image in a study.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="st-rec-service">
                <title>Study Reconciliation Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="st-stat-service">
                <title>Study Status Service</title>
                <para>
                    used to update Study Status triggered by receive
                    of General Purpose Performed Procedure Step N-CREATE-RQ with particular
                    Performed Work Item Code by General Purpose Performed Procedure Step SCP.
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="st-mgmt-scp-service">
                <title>Private Study Management Service SCP</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="st-mgmt-scu-service">
                <title>DICOM Modality Worklist SCU</title>
                <para>
                    used to forward 
                   messages received by private Study Management Service SCP Service. You must use the Content edit 
                    service to identify where study information updates are sent and received. Use the values in the 
                   CalledAETitle and the CallingAETitle attributesto configure
                   specific forwarding rules in this StudyMgtScu Service for study information updates
                   received from the Content Edit Service
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="fsm-status-service">
                <title>Check File Status Service</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="tls-conf-service">
                <title>TLS Configuration</title>
                <para>
                </para>
            </sect3>
            
            <sect3 id="xdsi-service">
                <title>XDS-I Service</title>
                <para>
                    Cross-enterprise Document Sharing for Imaging. (Imaging Document Source actor)
                </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

  </sect1>
</chapter>