<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="dcm4chee-installation" revision="1">
  <title>Installation Instructions</title>

  <sect1 id="install-requirements" revision="1">
    <title>Minimum System Requirements and Supporting Software</title>

    <para>dcm4chee is a Java-based application for the management of digital
    clinical objects. As such, it should be run under the best hardware
    available for production systems. The minimal system configuration is as
    follows:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>512 MB RAM</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>100 MB hard disk space (in addition to archive disk space for
        object storage and caching)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>400 MHz CPU or better</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>dcm4chee requires a database to store transient and permanent
    information from the clinical workflow and objects. The authors of
    dcm4chee realize that database expertise varies from site to site, and has
    included support for several different databases for deployment with the
    archive. The list of supported databases is:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>PostgreSQL 8.1.x</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>MySQL 4.1+</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Oracle 9i/10g</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SQL Server</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>DB2 8.1+</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis>Additional Software Notes</emphasis></para>

    <para>dcm4chee is a Java-based application. It requires the installation
    of the JDK version 1.4.2 or higher. JDK version 5 is recommended for the
    best performance and stability.</para>

    <para>For image compression/decompression, dcm4chee 2.8.x utilizes Sun's
    Java Advanced Imaging (JAI) Image I/O Tools 1.0_01. The binary
    distribution packages of dcm4chee 2.8.x already includes the necessary
    JARs and native libraries for Windows and Linux i586. For Solaris support,
    you need to download the software package from Sun at <literal><ulink
    url="http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jai/downloads/download-iio-1_0_01.html">http://java.sun.com/products/java-media/jai/downloads/download-iio-1_0_01.html</ulink></literal>
    and replace the Linux version of <literal>libclib_jiio.so</literal> in
    <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin/</literal> with the file of the same name from
    the Solaris JAI Image IO distribution.</para>

    <para>dcm4chee depends heavily on the JBoss (<literal><ulink
    url="http://www.jboss.org">http://www.jboss.org</ulink></literal>) application
    server for its infrastructure. It is not necessary to download JBoss (as
    dcm4chee is pre-packaged within JBoss), but viewing the online (or
    downloaded) JBoss documentation will assist a great deal in learning the
    dcm4chee directory structure, and how the product operates under the
    covers. JBoss services such as XMBeans, JBossMQ (JMS), and EJB (Session
    and Entity beans) are utilized by dcm4chee.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="install-steps" revision="1">
    <title>Installation Steps</title>

    <para>Installing dcm4chee is fairly easy:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Download the binary distribution of dcm4chee for the database of
        your choice from the Files page of the dcm4che project page on
        SourceForge (<literal><ulink
        url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/dcm4che/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/dcm4che/</ulink></literal>).
        If you do not see a distribution for your database, you will have to
        build dcm4chee from the source code. See  <xref linkend="dcm4chee-build"/> for instructions on doing
        so.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Once downloaded, extract the distribution package into your
        desired destination directory. Avoid using a directory path that
        contains spaces though, as that may cause problems when running the
        application from the command line.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Install the database software of your choice (keeping in mind
        the supported database systems) if you have not already done so. Keep
        in mind that the database software that you install (or have
        installed) must match the version of dcm4chee that you downloaded. For
        example, if you want to use PostgreSQL with dcm4chee then you should
        download the dcm4chee-standalone-psql-2.8.2.zip file from
        SourceForge.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>If using a database other than MySQL or PostgreSQL you will need
        to copy an apropriate JDBC Driver for the database to
        <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/lib/</literal>. This is not
        necessary for MySQL or PostgreSQL because the binary distribution of
        dcm4chee already contains the correct JDBC drivers for these database
        systems.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Verify that your database installation has TCP/IP socket access
        available.</para>

        <para>For example, with PostgreSQL you can check the pg_hba.conf file
        for your database:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
$PGDATA/pg_hba.conf:
# IPv4 local connections:
host    all         all         127.0.0.1/32          trust
        ]]></programlisting>

        <para>With Oracle, you can verify that the TNS Listener is
        enabled:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
C:\>netstat -b -p TCP
Active Connections
  TCP    localhost:1284               host.domain.com:1521     ESTABLISHED     1788
  [ORACLE.EXE]

  TCP    localhost:1521               host.domain.com:1284     ESTABLISHED     1816
  [TNSLSNR.exe]
        ]]></programlisting>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Initiate the archive database instance (named pacsdb) using the
        create DDL script located in
        <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/sql/create.xxx</literal>.</para>

        <para>For example, with PostgreSQL on a Unix-based system:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
> export PGUSER=postgres
> createdb pacsdb
> psql pacsdb -f DCM4CHEE_DIST/sql/create.psql
        ]]></programlisting>

        <para>To initialize a MySQL database on a Unix-based system:</para>

        <programlisting><![CDATA[
> mysql -uroot
mysql> create database pacsdb;
mysql> grant all on pacsdb.* to 'pacs'@'localhost' identified by 'pacs';
mysql> \q
> mysql -upacs -ppacs < DCM4CHEE_DIST/sql/create.mysql
        ]]></programlisting>

        <para><emphasis>Note</emphasis>: If you wish to take advantage of
        specific features of your RDBMS such as tablespaces, partitioning,
        etc. you will need to implement them on your own. This can sometimes
        be done with the tools that come with the database, or by modifying
        the DDL script before running it. If you make changes to the DDL
        script that you think might be useful to the wider audience, please
        submit them to the dcm4che-users listserv.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Adjust the dcm4chee database connection pool settings in
        <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/deploy/xxxx-ds.xml</literal> to
        suit your environment. This includes the user name and password that
        the application should use when obtaining connections. In addition,
        JBoss allows for the configuration of other aspects of the connection
        pool. Although the default settings are fine for basic deployment
        scenarios, the following may be added to the XML file in order to tune
        the connection pool:</para>

        <para><programlisting>&lt;!--example of how to specify class that determines if exception means connection should be destroyed--&gt;
&lt;!--exception-sorter-class-name&gt;org.jboss.resource.adapter.jdbc.vendor.DummyExceptionSorter&lt;/exception-sorter-class-name--&gt;

&lt;!-- this will be run before a managed connection is removed from the pool for use by a client--&gt;
&lt;!--&lt;check-valid-connection-sql&gt;select * from something&lt;/check-valid-connection-sql&gt; --&gt;

&lt;!-- The minimum connections in a pool/sub-pool. Pools are lazily constructed on first use --&gt;
&lt;min-pool-size&gt;5&lt;/min-pool-size&gt;

&lt;!-- The maximum connections in a pool/sub-pool --&gt;
&lt;max-pool-size&gt;20&lt;/max-pool-size&gt;

&lt;!-- The time before an unused connection is destroyed --&gt;
&lt;!-- NOTE: This is the check period. It will be destroyed somewhere between 1x and 2x this timeout after last use --&gt;
&lt;idle-timeout-minutes&gt;0&lt;/idle-timeout-minutes&gt;

&lt;!-- sql to call when connection is created
&lt;new-connection-sql&gt;some arbitrary sql&lt;/new-connection-sql&gt;
 --&gt;

&lt;!-- sql to call on an existing pooled connection when it is obtained from pool 
&lt;check-valid-connection-sql&gt;some arbitrary sql&lt;/check-valid-connection-sql&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;!-- example of how to specify a class that determines a connection is valid before it is handed out from the pool
&lt;valid-connection-checker-class-name&gt;fully qualified name of class to use&lt;/valid-connection-checker-class-name&gt;
--&gt;

&lt;!-- Whether to check all statements are closed when the connection is returned to the pool,
     this is a debugging feature that should be turned off in production 
&lt;track-statements/&gt; 
--&gt;</programlisting></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Set the JAVA_HOME environment variable to your JDK installation
        directory.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Adjust the Java heap settings for the application</para>

        <para>[Windows]: <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin/run.bat:</literal>
        <programlisting>rem Sun JVM memory allocation pool parameters. Modify as appropriate.
set JAVA_OPTS=%JAVA_OPTS% -Xms128m -Xmx512m</programlisting></para>

        <para>[Linux/Unix]: <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin/run.conf</literal>
        <programlisting># Specify options to pass to the Java VM.
JAVA_OPTS="-server -Xms64m -Xmx200m -Djava.awt.headless=true ..</programlisting></para>

        <para>Keep in mind the available RAM and memory requirements of other
        processes running on the hardware. For example, iif only 512 MB RAM is
        available on the machine, you should decrease the default value from
        <literal>-Xmx512m</literal> (on Windows to)
        <literal>-Xmx300</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Optional:</emphasis> Upon installation, all DICOM services are
        pre-configured with <classname>DCM4CHEE</classname> as the Application
        Entity Title (AE Title, or AET). Although it is possible to modify
        this default configuration at a later date through the Web-based
        administrative console, it is more efficient to replace
        <classname>DCM4CHEE</classname> with <classname>YOUR_AET</classname>
        in <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/conf/xmdesc/*.xml</literal>
        using utilities provided by your platform.</para>

        <para>For example, on GNU Linux:</para>

        <para><computeroutput>&gt; find
        DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/conf/xmdesc -exec \ sed -i
        s/DCM4CHEE_DIST/YOUR_AET/g '{}' ';'</computeroutput></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You're all done and ready to verify the installation.</para>
        
        <para>After verifying that the application is installed and running correctly, you may want to install it as a Windows service or Unix daemon.</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Stop the application (type <literal>ctrl-c</literal> in the console window).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Windows: install dcm4chee as a Windows service executing <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin/install_service.bat</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Redhat Linux: copy the init script <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin/dcm4chee_init_redhat.sh</literal> to <literal>/etc/init.d/</literal>
                    and adjust it according to the dcm4chee installation location, the JDK installation location,
                    and which user the dcm4chee should run under.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    
  </sect1>
  
    <sect1 id="install-verification" revision="1">
        <title>Verify the Installation</title>
        
        <para>Navigate to the <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/bin</literal> directory, and execute the
        run.bat or run.sh script, as appropriate for your operating system.
        Your output should look like the following and contain no error or
        exception messages:</para>
    
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
===============================================================================
.
  JBoss Bootstrap Environment
.
  JBOSS_HOME: C:\apps\dcm4chee-standalone-psql-2.8.2\bin\\..
.
  JAVA: C:\jdk1.5.0_06\bin\java
.
  JAVA_OPTS:  -Dprogram.name=run.bat -Xms128m -Xmx512m
.
  CLASSPATH: C:\jdk1.5.0_06\lib\tools.jar;
    C:\apps\dcm4chee-standalone-psql-2.8.2\bin\\run.jar
.
===============================================================================
.
14:46:16,046 INFO  [Server] Starting JBoss (MX MicroKernel)...
14:46:16,046 INFO  [Server] Release ID: JBoss [Zion] 4.0.3SP1 (build: 
    CVSTag=JBoss_4_0_3_SP1 date=200510231054)
...
...
...
14:46:50,626 INFO  -> [JkMain] Jk running ID=0 time=0/60  config=null
14:46:50,636 INFO  -> [Server] JBoss (MX MicroKernel) [4.0.3SP1 (build: 
    CVSTag=JBoss_4_0_3_SP1 date=200510231054)] Started in 34s:580ms
        ]]></programlisting>        
        
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Connect to the Web-based User Interface (default URL is <literal><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/dcm4chee-web/">http://localhost:8080/dcm4chee-web/</ulink></literal>)
                of the archive using any Web Browser (most tested are Mozilla Firefox and
                Microsoft Internet Explorer v6.x). You should get the User Login Screen.
                Login in using the default Administrator account <literal>admin</literal>, with password <literal>admin</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>Connect to the JBoss JMX Console (default URL is <literal><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/jmx-console/">http://localhost:8080/jmx-console/</ulink></literal>)
                and login in using the default Administrator account <literal>admin</literal>, with password <literal>admin</literal>.</para>
                
                <para>Follow the link <literal>service=FileSystemMgt</literal> to the  
                            File System Management service configuration page under the <literal>dcm4chee.archive</literal> heading.</para>
                            
                <para>Invoke the operation addOnlineFileSystem(), with a directory path argument specifying
                            where the archive shall store received objects/images.</para>
            
                <para><emphasis>Note:</emphasis> If no Storage File System is configured, the archive will auto-configure
                    <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/archive</literal> as the Storage File System when the
                    the first object/image is received.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Optional:</emphasis> In the default configuration, received images are stored 'as is'
                    - meaning that no compression is performed. Lossless (or other types of) compression of received
                    uncompressed images can be activated by the <literal>CompressionRules</literal> attribute in the
                    Storage SCP Service (<literal>service=StoreScp</literal>) configuration page.  For example, set it
                    to <literal>JLSL</literal>, to compress all types of images received from any Storage SCU with
                    JPEG-LS Lossless codec.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>Optional:</emphasis> The directory used for caching generated JPEG representations
                    of archived images requested by Web Access to DICOM Persistent Objects (WADO)
                    can be specified by the <literal>CacheRoot</literal> attribute in the 
                    the WADO Service (<literal>service=WADOService</literal>) configuration page. 
                    Default: <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/wadocache</literal>.</para>
                
                <para>The directory used for caching generated PDF representations of archived
                    Structured Report Documents requested by IHE Retrieve Information for Display
                    (RID) Services can be specified with the <literal>CacheRoot</literal> attribute in 
                    the RID Service (<literal>service=RIDService</literal>) configuration page. 
                    Default: <literal>DCM4CHEE_DIST/server/default/ihe_rid_cache</literal>.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>Send some objects/images to the archive's Storage SCP, using the 
                    send utility of the dcm4che14 package, the dcm4che2 package, or another Storage SCU of your choice.</para>
                    
                <para>If you're using dcm4che14, see <xref linkend="dcmsnd"/>.  If you're using dcm4che2, see below for an example:</para>
                
                <programlisting><![CDATA[
> dcm4che-2.0.6/bin/dcmsnd DCM4CHEE@localhost:11112 ~/mesa/storage/modality/MR
                ]]></programlisting>  
                    
                <para>Refresh the Web Interface (<literal><ulink url="http://localhost:8080/dcm4chee-web/">http://localhost:8080/dcm4chee-web/</ulink></literal>), which should 
                    now show the the list of received studies.</para>
                    
                <para>Expand a study row to show contained series. Expand one of these series
                    to show contained instances. In the case of images, you can follow the image
                    icon on the right to invoke an HTTP WADO request for a JPEG presentation of
                    this image which will be displayed in a separate browser window.</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>To test object retrieval, you will need an external Storage SCP acting as
                    the Destination using the DICOM Receiver utility of the dcm4che14 package, the dcm4che2 package, or another Storage SCP of your choice.</para>
                    
                <para>If you're using dcm4che14, see <xref linkend="dcmrcv"/>.  See below for a dcm4che2 example:</para>
                
                <programlisting><![CDATA[
> dcm4che-2.0.6/bin/dcmrcv 11113
13:55:14,782 INFO   - Start listening on 0.0.0.0/0.0.0.0:11113
Start Server listening on port 11113
                ]]></programlisting>  
                
                <para>Before initiating the retrieve, you will need to configure an additional Application Entity (AE) Title identifying
                    your Move Destination using the "AE Management" function of the Web User Interface.  For example:</para>
                
                <programlisting><![CDATA[
AE Title: DCMRCV
Hostname: localhost
Port:     11113
                ]]></programlisting>  
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem>
                <para>Switch back to the Study List (the Folder view) and mark studies to retrieve using the
                    check box on the right.  Select "DCMRCV" as the send destination in the combo box
                    above and click on the send button left from it.</para>
                    
                <para>Alternatively, you could initiate a C-MOVE with the utility of your choice with DCMRCV as the destination AE Title.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        
        <para>If everything worked, you are ready to start using dcm4chee.  If not, post your questions to the dcm4che-users listserv.</para>
    
    </sect1>
</chapter>